# 大家好 等一下 我就去把那個兄弟家的那個蜂蜜 (註︰他雖然確是說蜂蜜，但這個是他經常說錯的，我想寫清楚一點，下一句的「養」很清楚是蜜蜂，但英文的Keep則不太清楚，會誤以為只是蜂蜜)
Hi everyone! In a while, I'll go and take, you know, my buddy's honey bees.
# 全部拉到我們這邊場裡面來養
I'm gonna keep them all here at my site.
# 你看 這裡環境 還有外面好多那個花花草草哦
Look! The environment here, there are also a lot of flowers and whatever plants outside.
# 都有
There's everything.
# 蜂蜜到了 (註︰他又双叒叕把「蜂蜜」和「蜜蜂」搞錯了)
The honey is here now.
# 蜜蜂哦
I mean the honey bees.
# 有沒有塞住
Are they sealed?
# 塞住了
Yes, they are.
# 你看 這個是堵住了的 它出不來 全部蜂蜜在這裡面 (註︰這個蜂蜜其實又是想說蜜蜂，所以用Pluaral)
Look! It's sealed here. They can't come out. All the honey are inside,
# 出不來 蜜蜂
they can't come out. I mean the honey bees.
# 放邊上 一路可以放過去
Put them on the side, and all the way up there.
# 你看 全部都放好啦 這裡一路過 放過來
Look! So they're all here, from there, all the way up, up to here.
# 十幾箱 明天再來搞 上面的
I now have a dozen of boxes. Let's go on tomorrow, and put them up there.
# 現在天色有點晚
Now it's a little bit late.
# 你看 今天又搬了一箱 搬了一些下來
Look! Today I've taken another box, another couple of boxes here,
# 那裡一車 好多蜂蜜在這裡
in the car there. There are a lot of honey.
# 你看 把這些蜂箱 放在這附近
Look! I put these beehives, all around here.
# 把這個蜂箱一打開 蜂蜜就可以出來啦 蜜蜂
Once the beehives are unsealed. The honey can come out, I mean the honey bees,
# 就可以出來啦
they can come out then.
# 這些蜂箱就放在這裡 等一下 晚一點
I'll simply leave the beehives here, for a while, till later.
# 要讓它先適應一下
I gotta let them get used to,
# 這裡的 環境
the environment, here.
# 然後再把這個拉開 額 蜜蜂就出來
And then once I pull this thing out, eh, then the honey bees will come out.
# 然後就會自己采蜜啦
Then they can collect the nectar on their own.
# 像現在肯定還不敢開 一開的話它全部跑啦
I dare not open them now, no way. They all are gonna run away.
# 下次我們拉皂就放到裡面去 裡面還可以放
Next time we can take them inside. There is still more room inside.
# 剛好今天大漠過來啦 你看 他在上面
It just so happens that Uncle Damo came to us today. Look! Here is up there.
# 我們要包頭哦
We need to push them to a dead end.
# 嗯
Um
# 不然抓不到啊
Otherwise you can't catch them.
# 先找啊 看哪一隻最好吃找出來
Let's see first, see which one is the most tasty.
# 全部吃的下嗎
Are you sure that you can finish all?
# 抓到的都賺了
Got it! It's worth more than the cost of my trip here.
# 賺了賺了
It's worth much more.
# 夠了夠了 一人一隻夠了 夠了夠了夠了
Enough, enough. We can have one each. Enough, enough, enough.
# 走走走走走 架火架火
Go, go, go, go, go,! Let's set the fire, set the fire!
# 這肉可以哦
Their meat is not bad, right?
# 可以可以
Not bad, not bad.
# 很香額 可以
It smells good, right?
It's not bad.
# 很香
It smells so good!
# 很香哈哈哈哈
Yes, it is. Ha ha ha ha!
# 我已經聞到香味了
I can already sense the smell now.
# 你看 這個蜂蜜 取點蜂蜜來刷那個雞
Look! This is honey. We take some honey and brush it onto the chicken.
# 做秘[SIC]汁烤雞
We're gonna make a honey grilled chicken.
# 我們 搞一小碗就行啦
We're, gonna take just a small bowl of honey.
# 不用搞太多
We don't need too much.
# 這才是原裝蜂蜜啊
This is exactly what original honey should be.
# 這邊的山都是甚麼花
What kind of flowers are there on the hill here?
# 嗯 都是 野花 百花 百花咯
Um, it's like...
Wild flowers?
# (註︰上句太多重疊，所以拆成兩句)
All different kinds of flowers.
It's multifloral.
# 就百花 這就百花蜜啊
So it's multifloral. And this is multifloral honey.
# 對
Yup!
# 我拿刀來把它切 切成一塊一塊
I'm gonna take a knife. I need to cut it, cut it into pieces.
# 直接吃 放到碗裡面來吃 嗯
We eat right away, from the bowl.
Um!
# 你割的時候蜜蜂還跑出來啦
The bees are coming out when you're cutting it.
# 嗯 我眼鏡去哪啦 哎呀 不管啦
Um? Where are my eye glasses? Aya! Forget it.
# 哦 好哦 正好 正好拿了這塊來
Oh! Nice!
Take this piece right, right here.
# 來 我來
Alright, let me do it.
# 用小力就可以啦 不用那麼那魯
Be gentle. Don't be too rude.
# 再來
Go on.
# 嗯~捧哦
Um! It's nice!
# 這個很靚
It's really beautiful!
# 你看 這種蜜是很好的蜜哦這種
Look! This kind of honey is really good honey, you know.
# 哦 掉了誒 不要浪費了
Oh! It drops! Ey! Don't waste it!
# 三秒鐘肉就不髒啊
It doesn't get contaminated in less than three seconds.
# 嗯 不要浪費 不要浪費
Um! Don't waste it, don't waste it.
# 它這花粉是茶花
The pollen here is from tea flowers.
# 嗯
Um
# 有茶花的味道
There's a scent of tea flowers.
# 嗯
Um
# 等下我們用來烤那個 蜜汁 蜜汁烤雞
We're gonna use it and make a, a honey, honey grilled chicken.
# 淡香 有點小淡香
Subtle fragrance. There's a subtle fragrance.
# 那個蠟 蠟特別濃 我這 這一 這一塊很濃
The beeswax, is exceptionally rich. The piece, this, this piece that I have here, is really rich.
# 這個你嚼一下這個蠟 越嚼越香
You can chew the beeswax, and then the fragrance would become more significant.
# 我們拿下去吃
Let's enjoy it down there.
# 你看 剛好今天人比較多哦
Look! It just so happens that there are quite a lot of people here today.
# 順便搞了兄弟家兩隻雞 我也湊了一個鴨
So I've taken two chickens from my buddy. I've also contributed a duck.
# 把它宰好啦 準備把它清理一下
I've already got them ready. I'm gonna wash and clean them.
# 清理一下
Wash them.
# 把這雞腌一下
Let me marinate the chicken.
# 放這裡
Put it here.
# 搞點鹽
Put some salt.
# 腌一下
Marinate it.
# 再搞點醬油
Then put some say sauce.
# 再加點
And also some,
# 料酒
cooking wine.
# 加完之後再加點
After that, let's put some,
# 加點這個油
put some, some oil.
# 再搞點生薑
And also some ginger
# 先把這個邊上割一點花出來
Let me slice it a few times on this side.
# 更入味 這樣就
It will then be, much more flavourful.
# 特別是這個 雞胸肉
Especially the, chicken breast,
# 雞胸肉最厚的
chicken breast is always the thickest.
# 好啦 再給它莫兩下就好啦
Alright! Rub it a few more times and that's it.
# 嗯 先腌半個小時先
Um! Marinate it for half an hour first.
# 把這個雞放下去過一下水
I put the chicken here and blanch it for a while first.
# 這小雞 小雞仔
It's a chicken, a small chicken.
# 剛好香菇也放下去一下過水
I'm also putting the shiitake mushrooms and blanch them together.
# 過了水就直接撈起來 就直接
After blanching, I can take them out, and then,
# 香菇 嘖 燜小雞
stew the mushrooms, with chicken right away.
# 好啦 直接把它蓋 蓋起來
Alright! Let me just cover, cover it right away.
# 這是以前的灶台哦 你看 現在還有用 大水沒把它沖走
This used to be our stove, and it's now still good. The flood didn't wash it away.
# 我們繼續用
Let's keep on using it.
# 你看 兩邊有火
Look! Fire on both sides
# 現在 火還沒升起來哦 搞點這個
Now we're waiting for the fire to glow. Here I have some...
# 嘗一下我們這邊的土特產 吃一下
This is our local specialty here. Have a try!
# 燙皮
It's "tang pi" (baked ground rice chips).
# 這個包裝可以哦
This package is not bad.
# 這一個特產哦
This is a local specialty, isn't it?
# 我吃了好多啦 上午我吃了好多啦
I've had a lot. I've already eaten a lot this morning,
# 我吃的都飽了
so much that I'm already full now.
# 河邊燒烤哦 別有一番風情
A riverside barbecue. It's really exotic.
# 但是要注意這種天氣還是比較熱 今天三十來度是吧
But you gotta pay attention to the weather. It's rather hot today. It's thirty some degrees, right?
# 三十六度 三十六 嗯
Thirty six degrees.
# (上一句分成兩句)
Thirty six.
Um.
# 所以要多喝水防止中暑
So we need to drink more water to prevent heat stroke.
# 只在那水裡也可以
Lying in the water also works.
# 也可以哦
It also works right?
# 防止中暑
It prevents heat stroke.
# 你看 把這個雞
Look! I'm gonna tie,
# 綁起來 綁起來再烤
tie up, tie up the chicken and then grill it.
# 剛好帶了個鐵絲來
It just so happens that I have a wire with me.
# 把它腳綁起來
I can tie up its feet.
# OK 你看 搞定
OK! Look! It's done!
# 哦 這樣 這樣大家看一下哦
Oh! Then, now, everybody have a look!
# 他這樣 按照華農兄弟這樣綁那雞就跑不了啦
Tying it up in Huanong's way can prevent the chicken from running away.
# 這樣你給它跑 它跑不了啦 你看
Then it can no longer run away even if you're not watching it. Look!
# 像這就是為甚麼要綁腳哦 綁腳的原因就在這裡
That's why he needs to tie up the feet. Here's the reason for tying up the feet.
# 誒 這樣跑不掉了嘛 跑不了了 跑不了了
Ey! Then it can no longer run away. No way, no way.
# 等一下這個火 等它滅 等它滅了再說
Let's wait until the fire, until the fire goes off.
# 哇 差不多可以烤啦
Wa! I think we can start grilling now.
# 我們刷點油
Let's brush some oil.
# 不然太乾啦
It would be too dry otherwise.
# 給它皮膚做下
I'm giving its skin,
# 做下潤滑
some moisturiser.
# 哎呀這個 炭都滅掉啦 沒甚麼火
Aya! The charcoals is not longer burning. There's hardly any fire.
# 回家裡烤算啦 現在太晚啦
Let's just grill it at home. It's too late now.
# 還沒吃晚飯
I still haven't had my dinner.
# 還沒吃 午飯 不然我帶回家裡
I still haven't had, my lunch. Well I'm taking it home.
# 肚子餓的很 還沒烤熟
I'm starving, but it still needs a longer time.
# 這個兄弟家的炭不行啊 我帶了 我拿著我家的炭來烤
This is my buddy's charcoal. It's no good. I'll take, I'm gonna grill with my own charcoal.
# 把這個火滅掉
Let's put off the fire here.
# 你看 這個家裡的燙也煲好啦
Look! The soup at home is also done,
# 雞 那個鴨也搞好啦 雞燙也煲好啦
chicken, and also the duck, and also the chicken soup.
# 搞兩塊 我先吃啦 我先吃了這些再說
Let me have some. I'm gonna eat first. I eat something here first.
# 人都餓的乾趴趴啦
I'm starving and am about to pass out.
# 誒呀 好香
Eya! It smells good!
# 味道太好吃啦
It tastes simply marvellous!
# 我們吃完飯接著烤那個雞
We'll have our lunch first and then continue with the chicken.
# 先把 先把午飯吃了再說
Let's, let's have our lunch first, before everything
# 你看 午飯都做好啦 我們先吃午飯吧
Look! Our lunch is here. Let's have our lunch!
# 你看 鴨子 南瓜 青菜 碗豆
Look! Here are duck, pumpkins, veggies, green peas,
# 蘿蔔
radish,
# 還有 紫薯豬 (註︰這個發音錯誤不應該直接翻譯，找個近似的找替)
and also, purple yam cock,
# 紫薯粥
purple yam congee.
# 開始開始
Let's start, let's start!
# 開始
Let's start!
# 吃完飯啦 就想吃西瓜
After lunch, now I want some watermelons.
# 上次我摘了兄弟家 搞了十幾個西瓜 現在還有
Last time, I've taken, taken dozens of watermelons from my buddy's place. Now I still have some.
# 今天就沒有啦 吃完這兩個
But no more today. These two are the last ones.
# 哇 鮮紅色
Wa! It's shining red.
# 這樣的西瓜肯定很好吃
This kind of watermelons is certainly tasty.
# 先端走一半
Take away this half first.
# 你去那裡搞 搞 搞這些 這些西瓜
Where did you get, get, get these, these watermelons?
# 後面搞的
I picked them back there.
# 還是兄弟家的咯
And I bet that they are from your buddy, right?
# 兄弟家大把 他家吃不完 我幫他吃一下
My buddy has a lot! He can't finish them. So I'm helping him.
# 嘿嘿嘿 我也在幫他吃
He he he! And I'm also helping him now.
# 等一下要不要一起去 搞一點
You wanna get some, together with me, in a while?
# 一會兒嗎
In a while?
# 誒 我剛剛到村裡面 村民去哪啦 跑完啦
Ey? I was just in the village. Where are the villagers. Did they all run away?
# 不知道 在田裡面乾活吧 看西瓜熟了
No ideas. I think they're working in the fields. the watermelons are ripe now.
# 不可能 現在十二點啦 十二點了一個村民沒看到
No, it's impossible. It's now twelve at noon, at noon and not even a single villager came into my eyes.
# 這個時候西瓜剛好成熟
The watermelons are becoming ripe in this period of time.
# 哦
Oh!
# 可能他們幾乎去搞西瓜啦
So I think almost everybody is picking the watermelons.
# 哦哦哦哦哦
Ohhhh.
# 一會我們去搞一點 再搞一點
Let's pick some, some more in a while.
# 我今天早 早上打電話給他
I phoned him this morning.
# 打了一早上他沒接 不知道幹嘛
I've been phoning for the whole morning. But he didn't answer. Who knows what he was doing.
# 我兄弟 哦 沒有接 對啊
My buddy
# (上一句分兩句)
Oh! He didn't answer.
Exactly
# 本來我說帶你去搞兄弟家西瓜的
Originally, I wanted to take you to pick some watermelons at my buddy's place.
# 反正我一路拍過來 我在村裡面一路拍
I was like, filming all along the way. We were filming all along the way in the village.
# 一個村民都沒有
But we saw not even one villager.
# 很奇怪
It's weird.
# 人比較少
Not many people are here.
# 現在人少是吧
There are not so many people now, right?
# 對 只有老人跟孩子
Yup! Only the elderlies and the children are here.
# 哦 老人孩子也沒看到
Oh! But I saw nobody, neither elderlies, nor children.
# 在家裡
They stay at home.
# 哦
I see.
# 今天上午沒把它烤熟 今天下午我們繼續
We were in the halfway this morning. So let's continue now in the afternoon.
# 今天上午的火候不猛
The fire this morning was not strong enough.
# 現在是拿了一個凳子給爸爸坐是不是
So you are bringing daddy a stool, aren't you?
# 謝謝謝謝謝
Thx, thx thx!
# 去 去那邊坐著玩啊 等下烤好雞就叫你來吃啊
Go! Have a seat over there. I'll call you when the chicken is done.
# 去 家裡坐好來
Get, get a seat inside.
# 擦點蜂蜜給它身上
Let me brush some honey onto its body.
# 精油Spa
Essential oil spa
# 給它接一下摩
I give it a massage.
# 額 還要按一下摩啊
Eh! It even needs a massage.
# (雞)脖子都快斷啦
Its neck is about to break.
# 小心一點
I gotta be careful.
# 全身都擦的到
It's brushed all over the body.
# 油 油光油光啊
It's oily, shining oily, right?
# 對呀 蜂蜜撚到它每一寸肌膚
Yup! The honey is brushed onto every inch of its skin.
# 嗯
Um
# 腳趾上也抺一點
And also on the toes
# 搞(好？) 開始 稍微再烤一下就可以了
Alright. Let's start. We just need to slightly grill it for another short while.
# 我先洗個手再來
I'll come back after washing my hands.
# 這雞烤好啦
The chicken is done.
# 來 大漠叔叔
Hey! Uncle Damo!
# 來 直接開始吃了哈
Alright! We can start eating right away.
# 嗯 來來
Um! C'mon, c'mon!
# 嗯 棒哦
Um! Excellent!
# 我也要
Me too!
# 不夠粗魯
You're not rude enough.
# 有點燙
It's a bit hot.
# 幫我拿一下
Hold it for me.
# 你直接放口袋裡面
Why don't you just put it in your pocket right away?
# 這一塊 這一塊
This piece, this piece...
# 我想吃這一塊 嗯好 你吃這一塊
I want this piece.
Alright! You take this piece.
# 怎麼樣
How is it?
# (拿不到) (註︰原字幕沒有這句，但刘星辰說得太清楚了，不想去掉)
I can't take it.
# 哦 很甜
Oh! It's so sweet!
# 嗯 加點蜂蜜還不錯
Um! The honey really makes a difference.
# 香不香
Is it good?
# 哇 我要吃肉
Wa! I want a piece of meat.
# 不要吃肉
You want meat, right?
# 嗯 有點燙
Um! It's a bit hot.
# 還要嗎
You want more?
# 你還要不要 你要不要皮 這個
You want more? You want a piece of skin? Here.
# 要要要 我要皮 我不要皮
Yea, yea, yea! I want skin!
No, I don't want!
# 皮才有味
The skin is the most flavourful.
# 兩下就被 被小孩搶光啦 我就吃了個雞頭哦
The kids finished, finished the whole chicken in seconds. And I only got the chicken head.
# 沒有啦
There's no more.
# 沒啦
Nothing more
# 要不要雞頭
You want chicken head?
# 嗯 味道很不錯
Um! It tastes really not bad.
# 好啦 下次我要烤五個來
Alright! Next time I'm gonna grill five chickens.
# 它這太少啦 這個
It's far from enough, you know.
# 一下就吃完啦
Everything is gone in a second.
# 幸好我搶得快 吃了三個
Lucky me, I was fast this time. So I had three pieces.
# 給你的 你最小的 寶貝
It's for you! You're the smallest, baby!
# 一起玩 一起玩
We play together, play together
# 它這 這是甚麼 這是 花灑 哈哈哈哈
It's a, what is it? It's a shower. Ha ha ha ha!
# 看一下這甚麼 這鏡子 哦
See what it is? It's a mirror, oh!
# 是不是
Isn't it?
# 這個是她化妝的
She uses it when she puts on the makeup.
# 是不是真的有用的 哎呀 真的有用
Is it a real mirror? Aya! It's real one.
# 匆匆忙忙的二天就過去啦
It's the end of a hectic day.
# 謝謝兄弟
Thank you man!
# 帶點我們本地的東西回去
Bring some, bring some of our local products back home.
# 這一次也有點美中不足
There is still some room for perfection.
# 美中不足
Some room for perfection
# 就是 還 還有嗎
I mean, are there, are there any more?
# 再 再給一點 再給一點
Give, give me more, give me more!
# 其實我還能拿的下 還能拿 能拿
In fact I can still take more.
I can, I surely can.
# 地址 地址 把地址給我們 我們到時候就寄
Address, address, give us your address and then we can send you.
# 不 我們現在能拿嗎 能拿就再拿一點吧
No. Can we take now? If yes, I can still take more.
# 誒誒 能拿 我們能拿
Ey, ey! Yes, we can take more.
# 額 我們還有後備箱
Eh! We still have an empty trunk.